Contact

mhmdabdh@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/mhmdabdh (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Python (Programming Language)

Unix

SQL

Languages

English

Tamil

Hindi

Certifications

Foundation Course on AutoCAD

Programming in "C"

ITIL® Foundation Certificate in IT Service Management

Publications

Augmented Reality And Sixth Sense Based Artificial Speaking Aid For The Mute

Mohammed Abdullah

DevOps Engineer | IIT Madras | Cybersecurity Chennai

Summary

Mohammed Abdullah is a creative engineer in the areas of IT Operations, Infrastructure Engineering, Site Reliability Engineering and DevOps. Apart from scaling these systems, he is also interested in digital businesses and researches on cyber-security products and its sales, while at IIT Madras.

Experience

Socure

Senior DevOps Engineer January 2020 - Present (8 months)

Chennai Area, India

Socure Inc., provides a real-time predictive analytics platform that combines the newest forms of ML and Al with digital, offline and social identity data to deliver the most accurate fraud analytics solutions. We are a high-growth Series-C startup based in NYC - Silicon Alley.

What I do:

Evaluate and implement tools, plugins and AWS services to scale CI/CD Infrastructure

Build containerized pipelines to deploy to AWS services

Root cause analysis of performance issues on AWS services like EC2, EBS, RDS, ELB etc.

Create Lambda functions to monitor and alert instabilities and perform system hardening

Fidelity Investments

5 years 6 months

Lead Software Engineer
January 2018 - December 2019 (2 years)

Chennai Area, India

Setting up CI/CD infrastructure and deployment pipelines Migration from legacy tools to industry standard DevOps tools Building new pipelines to deploy to Amazon Web Services (AWS)

AWS Services - S3, EC2, EMR, CloudWatch

Exploration on deploying to all Public Clouds such as AWS, Azure and OpenStack

SRE initiatives to stabilize the CICD tool offering and provide a stable development environment

Senior Software Engineer

July 2014 - December 2017 (3 years 6 months)

Chennai Area, India

I am supporting multiple applications and working on incidents and problem tickets which arise in the applications, raise by users. I am also responsible for keeping the applications up and running at all times and involved in the patching activities to keep the application servers up to date. The primary application which I support is a HP product named PPMC. The product was recently upgraded from version 9.1 to 9.3 and I traveled to Ireland to support the development team in the upgrade activities.

Systems Reliability Engineering
October 2016 - November 2016 (2 months)

County Galway, Ireland; Dublin, Ireland

- -Volunteered to join the initiative of SRE
- -Identified tools such as Enterprise Stash, Enterprise JIRA, Enterprise UDeploy and stabilizing them
- -Working on administering the servers on which these applications are hosted
- -Working with development team to address the root cause for outages and putting in temporary and permanent fixes
- -Serving as a bridge between Development and Operations
- -Liaising with vendors to find ways to optimize and improve performance with better management using existing infrastructure
- -Employ best practices in server administration and application hosting

Subject Matter Expert

April 2016 - April 2016 (1 month)

United States, Boston Area

- .-Identified to work with US partner to play the role of SME in India
- -Work with US partner to organize and extensively document the application knowledge on HP PPMC and interfacing applications
- -Identify the SPOFs and put in checks and processes in place to ensure business continuity

- -Create a knowledge base of the moving parts and understand them and plan for future automation and development activities
- -Define methodologies and processes which will help exceed customer expectations
- -Review Production Readiness with development, infrastructure and DBA teams
- -Liaison with Project Managers, Development Managers, HP Representatives for product compatibility issues
- -Guide and mentor the India team on supporting the PPMC application

Application Upgrade Support June 2015 - July 2015 (2 months)

County Galway, Ireland

- -Represented the support team from India
- -Enabled the development team during upgrade of application HP PPMC to v9.3 which has a user base of approximately 40,000
- -Assisted in implementation and testing and identifying bugs and defects
- -Reducing cycle time by identifying issues proactively and classifying them as known issues and communicating to customers
- -Providing updates to senior management on the status of the upgrade
- -Communicating and training the India team on addressing the various issues post production validation

Infosys

5 years 1 month

Senior Systems Engineer September 2011 - June 2014 (2 years 10 months)

In addition to Global Maxtrad Support:

- -Support the third party reporting tool "Actuate Professional v10" for reporting.
- -Maxtrad contains ~300 reports related to the different trade finance products
- -Address customer queries regarding bad data, usability issues, new requirements
- -Fix issues or data discrepancies arising in these financial reports. This code was in the Actuate Basic programming language.
- -Perform code review with developers
- -Represent support team in the CAB conference calls
- -Mentor and provide KT to new team members
- -Shift Lead and SPOC for offshore team during US business hours

Systems Engineer

January 2010 - September 2011 (1 year 9 months)

- -Responsible to support and enhance the Royal Bank of Scotland's trade finance application.
- -The application named "Maxtrad" is built using VB6 with an Oracle database. Link: www.maxtrad.com
- -Learn the business logic behind various modules of Trade Finance and advise the customer facing team with the technical specifications and workflows (Import LC, Export LC, Guarantees, Direct Collections, Import Collections)
- -Adhere to customer SLA and resolve incident tickets
- -Fixed a number of bugs in the Presentation and Business Layer (ASP, VB6) and in the Database layer (Oracle)
- -Open problem tickets for recurring incidents
- -Perform non-prod testing of all fixes identified (SIT, UAT, PreProd) and PROD validation
- -Participate and represent the support team in high impact incident recovery calls
- -Participate in DR testing
- -Daily handover with onsite team
- -Sent routine reports to premium customers and later automated these reports
- -Provide skeleton and on-call support during holidays and other agreed nonbusiness hours

Software Engineer Trainee

June 2009 - December 2009 (7 months)

Trained in C, C++, RDBMS, HTML, .Net3.5 Framework and other tools and technologies.

Education

Indian Institute of Technology, Madras

Executive Master of Business Administration (2019 - 2021)

ShARE - Growing a new generation of leaders

ShARE's Leadership programme of excellence (2019 - 2021)

Anna University

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.), Mechanical Engineering (2005 - 2009)

St.Michael's Academy

Schooling, Biology, Physics, Chemistry, Math · (1991 - 2005)